駅[えき]:station, 向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|, 子供たち[こどもたち]:children
（ヤサコ）
駅向こうの子供たちのウワサでは
According to rumors among the kids from the other side of the station,
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 最も[もっとも, もとも]:most/extremely, 深い[ふかい]:deep|profound|dense||, 部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part
古い空間の最も深い部分には
in the deepest part of obsolete Space
危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, イリーガル:illegal, 住む[すむ]:to live (of humans)/to reside/to inhabit
危険なイリーガルが
住んでいるそうです
lives a dangerous Illegal.
（ヤサコ）
京子(きょうこ) どこー？
Kyoko!
The Boys from the
Other Side of the Station
Where are you?
She's got no sense of direction at all.
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 音痴[おんち]:tone-deafness|tone-deaf|having no sense (of something)
ったく…
方向音痴なんだから
地図[ちず]:map
にしても この地図―
Anyway, this map never works at critical moments...
肝心[かんじん]:essential/fundamental/crucial, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 役に立つ[やくにたつ]:to be helpful/to be useful
肝心なときには
必ず役に立たないわね
Kyoko's Position Unknown
霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray
あっ 霧だわ
The fog.
地図[ちず]:map, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
そういえば 地図が使えないとき
いつも古い空間が近くにあった
Now that I think about it,
whenever I couldn't use the map, there was an obsolete Space nearby...
駅[えき]:station, 向こう[むこう]:opposite side|over there|the other party|, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
駅向こうは
まだ探してなかったわ
Right, I didn't search on the other side of the station!
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
あそこまで行けば
古い空間が見つかるかも
If I go there, maybe I can find an obsolete Space!
迷子[まいご]:lost child/lost person/stray child, 呼び出し[よびだし]:call|usher who calls the names of wrestlers, sweeps the ring, etc.|telephone number at which a person without a telephone can be reached||, いたす:to do
（アナウンス）
迷子のお呼び出しをいたします
Service call for a missing child.
お母様[おかあさま]:mother
小此木(おこのぎ)優子(ゆうこ)ちゃん
お母様がお待ちです
Miss Yuko Okonogi!
Your mother is waiting for you.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 小学校[しょうがっこう]:primary school/elementary school/grade school, 組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting
小此木優子ちゃん
第三小学校６年３組
Miss Yuko Okonogi!
私のこと？
Me?
Third municipal elementary school,
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 小学校[しょうがっこう]:primary school/elementary school/grade school, 組[くみ]:set (of items)|group (of people)|typesetting
小此木優子ちゃん
第三小学校６年３組
sixth grade, class three...
ベージュ:beige, 洋服[ようふく]:Western-style clothes (cf traditional Japanese clothes), 丸い[まるい, まろい]:round/circular|harmonious, メガネ:spectacles/glasses
ベージュのお洋服に丸いメガネの
小此木優子ちゃん
She is wearing beige clothes and round glasses.
Her name is Yuko Okonogi.
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
や… やめて！
St-St...
Stop it!
迷子[まいご]:lost child/lost person/stray child
迷子は京子のほうでしょ
Kyoko was the one who got lost, wasn't she?!
アナウンス:announcement, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
なんで私を
アナウンスで捜すのよ！
Why on earth did you make the announcer call ME?!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（静江(しずえ)）キョウちゃんは
すぐ戻ってきたわ
Kyo came back right away.
You disappeared, and your cell phone was out of range.
っきり:only/just|since, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
あなたは行ったっきりで
電話もつながらなかったじゃない
街[がい]:.. street/.. quarter/.. district, 街[まち, ちょう]:town|street|109.09 m||, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
それは この街の空間が
おかしいせいなの
That's because the Space in this town is weird.
せいにする:to lay the blame on/to put the fault on
そんなもののせいにして
Stop blaming that.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 音痴[おんち]:tone-deafness|tone-deaf|having no sense (of something)
あなたは
昔から方向音痴なんだから
You've never had a sense of direction.
方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action)
（京子）方向ウンチ！
You're direction-poop!
京子が言うな！
Look who's talking!
昔[むかし]:olden days/former
（静江）昔っからよ
I remember that
迷子になる[まいごになる]:to get lost/to become lost/to go astray, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
金沢(かなざわ)でも迷子になって
大変だったじゃない
the same thing happened a long time ago in Kanazawa, and we had a hard time.
葬式[そうしき]:funeral
それに ほら
おじいちゃんのお葬式のときだって
And also...
Yeah, back at Grandpa's funeral.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, ほじくり出す[ほじくりだす]:to pick something out (nose, hole, etc.)|to pry (into people's private affairs)
そんな昔のことまで
ほじくり出さないでよ
Stop digging up all that ancient crap.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
どうせ またメガネのことでも
考えてたんでしょ？
Anyway, you were still thinking about your glasses, weren't you?
かげん:(moon's) last quarter, かげん:lower limit|infimum, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 脳[のう]:brain|brains/mind, 脳[なずき]:brain/skull/head
いいかげんにしないと そのうち
メガネ脳になっちゃうわよ
If you don't cut it out,
you'll become glasses-addicted.
何よ それ
What the heck?
What's wrong?
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, なさる:to do
どうしたの？　ほら 乗りなさい
Get in the car.
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||
乗らない
I'm not gonna ride.
What? You're still being capricious at your age?
何スネてんのよ ６年にもなって
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
（ヤサコ）
ちょっと探したい場所があるから
あとで１人で帰る
There's a place I want to search.
I'll come back later, by myself.
なさる:to do
（静江）
ちょっと待ちなさいよ 優子！
Hey! Wait!
Yuko!
年生[ねんせい]:pupil in ... year/student in ... year, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
私 もう６年生よ
ちゃんと帰れるもん
I'm already in sixth grade!
I'm able to get back home by myself!
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil
（一小の生徒１）ユウコだと？
Yuko, she said?
道に迷う[みちにまよう]:to lose one's way/to get lost
（静江）
また道に迷っても知らないわよ
If you get lost again, it's none of my business, got it?
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
絶対に迷わないもん！
I absolutely won't get lost!
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
ま… 迷ったわ
I-I got lost!
やっぱ:too/also|still, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 音痴[おんち]:tone-deafness|tone-deaf|having no sense (of something), かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
ハァ… やっぱ方向音痴なのかしら
So I really have no sense of direction...
生[き]:pure/undiluted/raw, 生[なま]:raw|natural|unprotected (i.e. not wearing a condom)||, 犬[いぬ, イヌ]:dog (Canis (lupus) familiaris)|snoop (i.e. a detective, a spy, etc.)|loser|, 珍しい[めずらしい]:unusual|new|fine (e.g. gift)
あら 生犬だわ　珍しい
Oh!
A real dog.
That's rare.
（ヤサコ）デンスケ！
Densuke!
デンスケ 待って！
Densuke, wait!
Yuko!
（メガばあ）
優子 どこ行くんじゃ？
Where are you going?
Poop!
（ヤサコ）ウンチ！
勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||, 走る[はしる]:to run|to travel (movement of vehicles)|to hurry to||
そうだ あのとき
デンスケが勝手に走り出して…
Right...
Back then, Densuke started running on his own...
And a bit later I met that person...
出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
そのあと
あの人と出会ったんだわ
What was that?
なんだっけ？
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
あのとき もっと大事なことが
あった気がする
It feels like,
something more important happened back then...
気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
（ヤサコ）
ここ 来たことある気がする
This place...
It feels like I've been here before...
気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of
ハァ… 気のせいか
It must be just my imagination...
Hey, you!
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil
（一小の生徒１）おい お前！
（ヤサコ）ハッ！
You...
お前 ユウコって名前か？
Is your name Yuko?
な… 何？
What?
I heard it just now.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill
（一小の生徒１）さっき聞いたぞ
お前 ユウコっていうんだな？
So, your name is Yuko.
I already know that!
分かってるんだぞ
You're...
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|
お前 第三小の天沢(あまさわ)ユウコだな
Yuko Amasawa, from the third elementary school!
Hey, guys.
おい お前ら出てこい
Come out.
Who are you guys?
な… 何よ あなたたち
We're from the first elementary school.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers
（一小の生徒１）第一小の者(もん)だ
So, you've been messing with our net lately!
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 縄張り[なわばり]:stretching a rope around/roping off|one's turf, 荒らす[あらす]:to lay waste|to invade|to troll (e.g. web forums)
最近 俺たちの縄張りを
荒らしてるようだな
W-Wait!
人違い[ひとちがい]:mistaking one person for another/(case of) mistaken identity
ちょ… ちょっと待って
あなたたち人違いしてるわ
You're confusing me with someone else!
My name is certainly Yuko, but...
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
確かに 私 ユウコだけど
天沢さんじゃ…
I'm not Amasawa!
So, you really are Yuko.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, やっぱり:too/also|still
（一小の生徒２）やっぱりユウコか
We finally got you.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, とうとう:finally/at last/ultimately, とうとう:clashing of swords/felling of trees/ringing of an ax, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
（一小の生徒３）
とうとう捕まえたぞ
Give us that  thing.
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
例のものを出してもらおうか
What thing?
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example
れ… 例のもの？
The kirabugs!
集める[あつめる]:to collect/to assemble/to gather
キラバグだよ
集めてるのは分かってるんだ
We know you're collecting them!
Give us the stuff now!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
早く出せ！
If you don't, we'll take 'em by force!
出さなきゃ力ずくで…
After her!
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, 追いかける[おいかける]:to chase/to run after/to pursue
（一小の生徒１）追いかけろ！
There she is!
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil, あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
（一小の生徒１）あそこだ！
ああ… どうしよう？
What should I do?
Here, here!
（タケル）こっち こっち
Quickly, get inside here!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
（タケル）早く この中に
（ヤサコ）わあっ！
Where did she go?
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 生徒[せいと]:pupil
どこ行った？
（一小の生徒２）いねえぞ
She's not here.
She must've taken the other street!
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
きっと さっきの道だ
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
急げ！
Hurry up!
ハァ…
急[きゅう]:urgent|sharp|rapid||
あっ ご… ごめんね
急にこんなことして
S-Sorry!
It was so sudden.
Those guys always want to bully new kids.
あいつら いっつも
よそから来た子を―
いじめる:to tease/to torment/to persecute
いじめようとするんだ
Uh, thank you!
ううん:no|er, well, ..., ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
う… ううん ありがとう
In any case, this is very...
にしても これって…
Yeah.
メガネをかける:to wear glasses/to put on glasses
うん　ここに入ると
メガネをかけてる人には―
If you go inside here, you're invisible to people who wear glasses.
姿[すがた]:figure|appearance|state||, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
姿が見えなくなるんだ
Is this an
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher
（ヤサコ）これは… 暗号？
encode?
Are you an encoder?
暗号[あんごう]:code/password/cipher, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
あ… あなた 暗号屋なの？
えっ？　ああ 違うよ
Ah... not really.
Someone must've drawn it and then left it here.
描く[えがく, かく]:to draw|to depict|to picture in one's mind|, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
これは誰かが描いて
残していったものなんだ
So this is...
それって…
Yeah,
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
（タケル）
うん あいつらが勘違いした―
it must've been made by that Yuko Amasawa they mistook you for.
仕業[しわざ]:deed (esp. negative)/act/action, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
天沢ユウコの仕業だよ きっと
Do you know her?
知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
知り合いなの？
Not at all!
全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely
いや 全然
Well, actually I got lost.
実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, 道に迷う[みちにまよう]:to lose one's way/to get lost, 方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 音痴[おんち]:tone-deafness|tone-deaf|having no sense (of something)
（ヤサコ）実は道に迷っちゃったの
私 方向音痴でさ
I have no sense of direction.
Where do you want to go?
どこまで行きたいの？
Well... err,
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ..., 大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 駅[えき]:station
え… えーっとね　大黒(だいこく)駅
Daikoku station.
Well, you see,
駅[えき]:station, あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
だって ほら 駅は あそこに…
the station is right there...
Oh, shoot...
（ヤサコ）あっ ヤダ…
方向[ほうこう]:direction/orientation|course (e.g. of action), 音痴[おんち]:tone-deafness|tone-deaf|having no sense (of something)
本当に方向音痴なんだね
So you really don't have a sense of direction.
I'm Takeru.
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|
僕 タケル　第一小の６年
I'm in sixth grade at the first elementary school.
I'm Yuko.
私 優子　三小の６年よ
I'm in sixth grade at the third elementary school.
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
ヤサコって呼ばれてる
Everybody calls me Yasako.
（タケル）
へえー ヤサコ… ヤサコか
Oh, Yasako...
Yasako, huh!
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
僕も そう呼んでいい？
Can I call you like that, too?
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
もちろん
Of course!
ヤ… ヤサコ
Ya-Yasako!
駅[えき]:station, 送る[おくる]:to send (a thing)|to take or escort (a person somewhere)|to bid farewell (to the departed)||, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
え… 駅まで送ってあげるよ
I-I'll take you to the station.
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
あ… ありがとう
Thank you.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, 風景[ふうけい]:scenery/scene|scene (e.g. of a crime)
（ヤサコ）ねえ ここって
昔からこんな風景だった？
Hey,
do you know if this area has always looked like this?
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
えっ？　うん 多分
Yeah, I think so.
駅[えき]:station, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, だいぶ:lengthy (of a book, etc.)/voluminous|most (e.g. most part), だいぶ:considerably/greatly/a lot, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
駅の近くは
だいぶ変わっちゃってるけど
But around the station, things have changed quite a lot.
What's wrong?
どうしたの？
やっぱり:too/also|still
やっぱり来たことある
I'm certain I've been here before!
ど… どこ行くの？
Wh-Where are you going?
駅[えき]:station
どうしたの？
駅に行くんじゃないの？
What's wrong?
Didn't you want to go to the station?
見覚え[みおぼえ]:remembrance/recollection/recognition
ここ 見覚えがあるの
I... remember this place.
そうなの？
Oh, really?
I know I'm saying something odd...
変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
私 変なこと
言ってるかもしれないけど
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu), 辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., 迷子になる[まいごになる]:to get lost/to become lost/to go astray
多分 小さい頃
この辺で迷子になったの
But I think that when I was a little girl,
I got lost here.
そして…
Something...
何かが… 何かがあったの
Something happened.
何かって… 何があったの？
Something?
What?
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 頃[ころ, ごろ]:(approximate) time|suitable time (or condition)|time of year, 頃[けい]:qing (Chinese unit of land area equal to 100 mu)
忘れてる 小さい頃だったし
I forget.
I was very little.
I'd like to remember.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
思い出したい
でも思い出せないの
But I can't.
Is it
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
（タケル）それは大事なことなの？
something very important?
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
うん 多分
Yeah... Maybe.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
一緒に捜そう
（ヤサコ）えっ？
Let's look for it together!
辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., 詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
この辺は僕のほうが詳しいから
一緒に捜せば見つかるかもしれない
I know this area better than you do.
If we look for it together, maybe we can find it!
で… でも
B-But...
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
ねえ どんな場所なの？
その捜してる場所
So, what kind of place is it?
The place you're looking for.
It's a place with stone stairs
石[いし]:stone|gem/jewel, 石[こく]:measure of volume (approx. 180.39 liters, 6.37 cub. ft.)|measure of a Japanese-style boat's loading capacity (approx. 278.26 liters), 階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase, 鳥居[とりい]:torii/Shinto shrine archway, ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.), 続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||
（ヤサコ）石の階段があって
その上に鳥居がずっと続いてるの
and many torii on it.
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals
もしかして あそこかも！
Maybe it's...
Yeah, maybe it's that place!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
ほら 早く！
Come on, hurry!
Okay!
Look, here!
ほら ここ
This must be it!
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
きっと ここだわ
Wait, Yasako!
止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
待って ヤサコ！　止まって！
Stop!
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||
（タケル）危ない！
Watch out!
Keep Out
I didn't know this shrine was being dismantled.
解体[かいたい]:demolition/disassembly|dissection (i.e. postmortem), 神社[じんじゃ]:Shinto shrine
（タケル）
解体中だったんだな この神社
But I'm glad you found
見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
だけど見つかってよかったね
捜してた場所
the place you were looking for.
ハァ… 違うの
This isn't the one.
Oh?
This isn't the place.
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 似る[にる]:to resemble/to look like|to be similar (in status, condition, etc.)
違う場所だわ 似てるけど
Even if it looks like it.
Is that so?
そうなの？
The stairs continued straight to the top.
階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase, まっすぐ:straight (ahead)/direct|straightforward, 伸びる[のびる]:to stretch|to make progress|to grow stale (soba)||
階段は まっすぐ上まで伸びてた
They didn't turn in the middle like this.
途中[とちゅう]:on the way/en route|in the middle of, 曲がる[まがる]:to bend|to turn|to be awry
途中で こんなふうに
曲がってなかったの
I see...
残念[ざんねん]:deplorable/bad luck/regret
そっか 残念だな
Too bad.
Hiwata Park
Is it just my imagination?
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
（ヤサコ）私の勘違いなのかなあ…
Even ants know where they're supposed to go.
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
アリでも
自分が行く場所を分かってる
But I can't find it.
見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something, 惨め[みじめ]:miserable/wretched/unhappy, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
でも 私は見つけられない
なんか惨めな気持ちだわ
I feel so pathetic.
I don't know what happened that day, but...
そこで何があったか知らないけどさ
If that place really exists, you'll certainly find it.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
本当にあったのなら
きっと見つかるよ
I don't know anymore
本当にあったかどうかも
よく分からなくなってきちゃった
whether or not it really existed.
Nah,
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly
いや きっと
本当にあったんだと思うよ
I'm certain it really exists.
At least,
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
（タケル）少なくとも こんなに
見つけたいって思ってる―
your strong desire to find that place is genuine, isn't it?
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal
ヤサコの気持ちは本物だろ？
If you keep searching with that feeling,
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
だったら その気持ちで捜せば
何かきっと見つかると思うよ
I'm sure you'll find it.
That real "something."
本当の何かが
You're such a good person.
あなた いい人ね
You saved me from those weird guys,
変[へん]:strange|unexpected|change||, 連中[れんちゅう, れんじゅう]:company/lot|troupe, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, 鳥居[とりい]:torii/Shinto shrine archway, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
変な連中から助けてくれたし
鳥居を捜すの手伝ってくれるし
you're helping me look for the torii...
Oh, I wish that all boys were like you.
男の子[おとこのこ, おとこのコ]:boy/male child/baby boy, 男の子[おのこ]:man/boy, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
男の子が みんな
あなたみたいだったらいいのに
Not at all!
そ… そんなことないよ
Come on, let's go!
ほら 行こうよ
Yes!
So,
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（タケル）
ねえ その場所で何があったの？
what happened there?
うーん:hmm/well, ひと言[ひとこと, いちげん]:single word/a few words/brief comment, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
（ヤサコ）うーん…
ひと言では言えないかな
I can't describe it in just few words.
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
（タケル）ふーん
いいことだったみたいだね
It must've been something beautiful.
Maybe it wasn't only beautiful.
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
いいことだけじゃ
なかったかもしれない
Something scary?
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 悲しい[かなしい]:sad/sorrowful
怖いこと？　悲しいこと？
Or sad?
Well, how was it?
両方[りょうほう]:both/both sides/both parties
どうだったかな？
その両方だったかも
Maybe both of those feelings.
But if we didn't find it after searching so hard,
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 実在[じつざい]:reality/existence, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
でも これだけ捜してもないんじゃ
実在しない場所だったかもね
maybe it means this place doesn't exist for real.
Maybe it was a dream.
夢[ゆめ]:dream
夢とか
Perhaps
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, 実在[じつざい]:reality/existence, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
もしかしたら
本当に実在しない場所かもしれない
this place doesn't exist "in reality."
But perhaps it wasn't a dream, either.
夢[ゆめ]:dream, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
でも 夢でもなかったかもしれない
What do you mean?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
どういうこと？
Were you wearing glasses back then?
メガネをかける:to wear glasses/to put on glasses
そのとき
メガネをかけてなかった？
I was.
かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
かけてたわ
So...
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
もしかして―
maybe you can only see this place when you're wearing glasses.
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
それはメガネでしか
見えない場所なんじゃ…
When wearing glasses?
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
メガネでしか見えない？
そんな場所があるの？
Do such places exist?
Obsolete Space.
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
古い空間さ
Obsolete...
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
古い空間？
Space?
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, いろんな:various, バージョン:version
（タケル）古い空間にも
いろんなバージョンがあるんだ
There are many versions of obsolete Space.
現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, データ:data/datum, 時差[じさ]:time difference
中には現実世界とのデータに
時差があって
Inside them, there can be a time difference between their data and the real world,
とっく:a long time ago|quickly/swiftly, とっく:special ward|special economic zone (China), なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
本当はとっくになくなったものが
見えたりする
so you might see places that disappeared long ago.
現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（ヤサコ）
現実にはない場所ってこと？
You mean... places that don't exist for real?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
でも確かに あの場所で 私…
But,
I'm sure I went to that place...
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
でも もし
そこが古い空間にあるとしたら―
Anyway,
if there's really obsolete Space near there,
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
急いで見つけなくちゃならない
we have to hurry and find it.
どうして？
Why is that?
（タケル）サッチーだよ
Because of Satchii.
側[そば, そく]:near/close|third person, 側[がわ, かわ]:side (of something, or taking someone's side)/part|(watch) case, めった:thoughtless/reckless|seldom (with neg. verb)
こっち側には
めったに来なかったけど
They never used to come around here...
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), 見かける[みかける]:to (happen to) see/to notice/to catch sight of
この１週間で
よく見かけるようになったんだ
but in the last week, I've seen them often.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 毎日[まいにち]:every day
（ヤサコ）私たちのほうは毎日よ
In our area, they're a daily thing.
おかげ:grace (of God)/benevolence (of Buddha)|assistance, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 小[しょう]:smallness|short month (i.e. having fewer than 31 days)|elementary school||, 小[こ]:small|slightly less than|somewhat|, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
おかげで三小の近くには
古い空間が１つもないわ
That's why there's no obsolete Space around the third elementary school.
（タケル）そっか
I see.
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
サッチーより早く見つけないと
We have to find it before Satchii, or...
（ヤサコ）そうね
You're right.
イマーゴ:imago, 使える[つかえる]:to be usable/to be serviceable/to be useful
イマーゴが使えるといいんだけどな
I wish I could use Imago, but...
イマーゴ:imago
イマーゴって？
Imago?
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 超能力[ちょうのうりょく]:extra-sensory perception/ESP|psychokinesis
（タケル）古い空間を見つける
メガネの超能力なんだ
It's a superpower in glasses that allows you to find obsolete Space.
都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore
都市伝説だけどね
It's just an urban legend, you know.
メガネをかける:to wear glasses/to put on glasses, 不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange, 声[こえ]:voice, 感覚[かんかく]:sense/sensation/feeling, 感じ取る[かんじとる]:to perceive/to sense/to take in
メガネをかけると
不思議な声や感覚を感じ取って…
When you put on your glasses and hear mysterious sounds or feel strange...
イマーゴ:imago
でも イマーゴは…
But,
this Imago...
大黒[だいこく]:god of wealth|monk's wife, 市[いち]:market/fair, 市[し]:city, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 消す[けす]:to erase|to turn off power|to extinguish|
大黒市は なんで あんなに
古い空間を消そうとするんだろ？
Why does Daikoku City want to delete all the obsolete Spaces so badly?
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, いろんな:various
古い空間には
いろんなウワサがあるから
There are many rumors about obsolete Space, you know.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 誤[ご]:mistake/error, 作動[さどう]:operation/functioning/running, 去年[きょねん, こぞ]:last year, 子供[こども]:child/children, だって:after all/because|but
電脳ナビを誤作動させたり
去年は子供もそれで死んだって
Like, it disturbs the cyber navi.
I heard that last year, a kid died in an accident that way.
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
それにしても
あんなに一度に見たのは初めてだ
But,
it's the first time I've seen so many of them together.
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
これはマズいな
（ヤサコ）マズいって？
This is very bad.
Why bad?
本格的[ほんかくてき]:genuine|full-scale|full-fledged, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
本格的に古い空間を
潰しに来たかもしれない
Maybe they came to totally erase any obsolete Space from the base.
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing, 消す[けす]:to erase|to turn off power|to extinguish|, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
早く見つけないと
今日にも消されてしまうかも
If we don't find it quickly,
it might even be deleted today!
…とは言っても―
But still...
当て[あて]:aim|expectations|something that can be relied upon||, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 見つかる[みつかる]:to be found/to be discovered
当てもなく捜しても
見つかるわけないしな
there's no way we can find it without some clues.
ねえ どうしたの？
Hey, what's wrong?
ヤサコ？
Yasako?
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
私 聞こえるの
I can hear it.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
聞こえるって何が？
What can you hear?
ヤサコ
Yasako!
別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother)
（ヤサコ）
あのあと あの人と別れたあと…
After that...
After I parted from that person...
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
どうしよう… 迷っちゃった
What can I do?
I got lost!
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
ここ さっきも通ったわ
I already passed by here earlier!
帰り道[かえりみち]:the way back or home/return trip, 出会う[であう]:to meet (by chance)|to meet (e.g. of rivers, highways, etc.)|to emerge and engage (an enemy)
私は帰り道が分からなくなって
何かに出会った
I got completely lost on the way home,
and I met something.
あれは 今から思えば…
If I think about it now,
I understand that it was...
イリーガル:illegal
イリーガルだわ
an Illegal.
昔[むかし]:olden days/former, イリーガル:illegal
そんな昔にイリーガルと？
So a long time ago, you met an Illegal?!
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
多分
Maybe.
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
でも うまく思い出せない
But
I can't remember well.
起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
あのとき何が起こったか…
What happened back then?
（ヌル）マイゴ ニ ナッタ…
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
なんて言ったの？
What did you just say?
マイゴ ニ ナッタ…
...2-3...
ニイサン ヲ サガシテイル…
I'm looking for...
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
（ヤサコ）何かを捜してた
He was looking for something.
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 迷子になる[まいごになる]:to get lost/to become lost/to go astray
何かを捜して
私と同じ迷子になってた
He was looking for something,
when he got lost, just like me.
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
タケル君の言うとおりだわ
It must be like you said.
イリーガル:illegal, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 階段[かいだん]:stairs/stairway/staircase, 鳥居[とりい]:torii/Shinto shrine archway
あのイリーガルのいた場所も
あの階段鳥居も…
Both the place where I met that Illegal,
and the place with the stairs and torii...
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
古い空間だわ
must be an obsolete Space!
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
あそこで何が起こったの？
What happened there?
ヤサコ！
Yasako!
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, この先[このさき]:beyond this point/from now on/after this
あのときと同じ…
この先にあるわ！
Just like that time!
It's at the end of this street!
ま… 待って！
どうしたの？　ヤサコ
W-Wait!
What's the matter with you? Yasako!
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
（タケル）古い空間だ
一体どうやって？
It's obsolete Space...
How on earth did you know?
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., イマーゴ:imago
さっきの話 イマーゴの…
That thing you were talking about...
the Imago!
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
多分 私 それかもしれない
Perhaps I can use it!
イマーゴ:imago, 超能力[ちょうのうりょく]:extra-sensory perception/ESP|psychokinesis, ホント:truth/reality/actuality
えっ イマーゴの超能力？
ホントに？
The Imago superpower?
Really?
It happened to me several times before.
今まで[いままで]:until now/so far/up to the present, 何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, ひそひそ:whisperingly, 声[こえ]:voice, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
今までも何度かあったの
ひそひそ言う声が聞こえて…
I start hearing a mysterious voice...
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
す… すごい！
A-Awesome!
何度[なんど]:how many times?/how often?, 試す[ためす]:to attempt/to test/to try out, 全然[ぜんぜん]:not at all (with neg. verb)|wholly/entirely
僕も何度か試してみたけど
全然ダメだったんだ
I tried a few times, too,
but I never succeeded!
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
ねえ どんなふうに聞こえるの？
So, what does it sound like?
メガネ:spectacles/glasses, スピーカー:speaker
メガネのスピーカーからなの？
それとも…
Does it come from the glasses' speakers?
Or somewhere else?
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), 道に迷う[みちにまよう]:to lose one's way/to get lost
私 デンスケを捜しに来て
道に迷っちゃったの
I came to look for Densuke, but I got lost.
おうち:hollow/low ground/basin, おうち:interior/backwoods/hinterland, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 道[みち]:road|distance|the way (of proper conduct, etc.)||, 道[どう]:road|way|Buddhist teachings||
おうちに帰る道 知らない？
Do you know the way back home?
シラナイ
I don't know...
What are you looking for?
捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
あなたは何を捜してるの？
…ニイサン
...Two, three.
顔色[かおいろ, がんしょく]:complexion/one's colour|countenance
ど… どうしたの？　顔色が…
Wh-What's wrong?
You're getting pale.
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect, 黒い[くろい]:black|dark|illicit, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal, 捜す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
そうだ 思い出したわ
あの黒い生き物が捜してたもの
That's right!
Now I remember!
I remember what that black creature was looking for!
...Four, two, three.
…ニイ サン
兄さん[にいさん, あにさん]:older brother|brother (as older-brother figure in friendly and or work relationship)|(vocative) young man
兄さん？
Two-three?
４４２３ ヲ サガシテイル
4-4-2-3...
I'm looking for that...
なぜ ４４２３を？
Why...
4-4-2-3?
Kyuu-chans!
キュウちゃんだ！
間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough
もう間に合わない！
We won't make it in time!
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
思い出せない
I can't remember...
あとちょっと…
あとちょっとなのに！
But it's only...
only a little bit more!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
（少年）
早く逃げるんだ ヤサコ！
Run away, quickly!
Yasako!
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
逃げろ！
Run!
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||
（タケル）
危ない！　行くな ヤサコ！
Yasako, don't go!
止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
（ヤサコ）止めないで！
きっと あの先に あの場所が…
Don't stop me!
I'm sure that at the end of this street, I'll find that place!
Cut it out and get the hell out of here!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
いいから早く ここを出るんだ！
思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
大丈夫？　何か思い出せた？
Are you okay?
Do you remember anything else?
ううん:no|er, well, ..., あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact
ううん
あんなの現実なわけがない
No...
There's no way it could be real.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 小さい[ちいさい]:small/little/tiny, 夢[ゆめ]:dream
きっと小さいときに見た
夢だったんだわ
It must be just a dream I had when I was little.
And by the way, why did you stop me so suddenly?
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
あなたこそ
なんで あんなに止めたの？
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, いろんな:various, バージョン:version, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（タケル）古い空間に いろんな
バージョンがあるって話 したよね？
As I told you, there are many version of obsolete Space.
Right.
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, バージョン:version
これがさっきの場所の
バージョンなんだ
This is the version from that place just now.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 霧[きり]:fog/mist|spray, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
5.20以上の古い空間は
霧が出るくらいなんだけど
Any Space prior to 5.20 causes the fog...
以下[いか, いげ]:not exceeding|below (e.g. standard)|the below-mentioned, バージョン:version, ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
それ以下のバージョンは
ヤバいらしいんだ
Versions older that that are dangerous, I believe.
ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.)
ヤバい？　ヤバいって どんな？
Dangerous?
What do you mean?
あくまで:to the end/to the bitter end|after all, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（タケル）
あくまで都市伝説の話なんだけど
Take it as just an urban legend, but...
あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 深い[ふかい]:deep|profound|dense||, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
あんまり深い所まで行くと
戻ってこれなくなるって…
Apparently, if you go too deep into obsolete Space,
you can't get back anymore.
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（ヤサコ）戻ってこれなくなる？
Can't get back anymore?
生身[なまみ, しょうじん]:living flesh/flesh and blood|physical body of Buddha or a bodhisattva, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, ズレる:to slide/to slip off/to get dislocated
そう 生身の体と電脳の体がズレて
Yeah.
Your real body and your cyberbody become shifted...
やがて:before long/soon|almost, 魂[たましい, だましい]:soul/spirit, 魂[こん]:Yang energy/spirit, あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person), しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
やがて 魂ごと あっちに
連れて行かれてしまうんだって
And before long,
even your soul is taken to the other side.
連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
（ヤサコ）
連れて行かれるって何に？
Taken?
By what?
（タケル）
僕も よくは知らないけど
I don't really know either.
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 見つける[みつける, みっける]:to discover|to locate|to be used to seeing
もし 君が本当に
古い空間を見つけられるんなら
But if you're able to find an obsolete Space,
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
１つ教えておいてあげる
I'll give you some advice.
This is another urban legend, but...
都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore, ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
これも都市伝説なんだけど
ヤバい空間で―
There's a rule one must never break in dangerous Space.
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), ルール:rule
絶対に守らなきゃならない
ルールがある
（ヤサコ）何？
What's that?
You must never take off your glasses
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 外す[はずす]:to unfasten|to remove|to leave|
新しい空間に戻るまで
絶対にメガネを外さないこと
until you go back to normal Space.
電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, ズレる:to slide/to slip off/to get dislocated, 外す[はずす]:to unfasten|to remove|to leave|
もし 電脳の体が
ズレたときに外すと…
If you take them off while your cyber body is shifted...
どうなるの？
What would happen?
二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
二度と戻れなくなるって
As I said, you couldn't get back anymore.
It must be just a legend!
作り話[つくりばなし]:fiction/made-up story/fable
（ヤサコ）そんなの作り話よ
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 都市[とし]:town/city/municipal, 伝説[でんせつ]:tradition/legend/folklore
きっと そうだね
でも都市伝説では―
You're probably right.
But in these urban legends,
there are kids that fell into a coma
意識[いしき]:consciousness|awareness|mano-vijnana (mental consciousness, cognizer of sensory information), 不明[ふめい]:unclear|unknown|ignorance
そのまま
意識不明になっちゃった子とか
死んだ子もいるって
or died.
いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
（ヤサコ）
いろいろ助けてくれてありがとう
Thank you for all your help!
楽しい[たのしい]:enjoyable/fun, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||
僕のほうこそ楽しかったよ
大変だったけど
It was a lot of fun for me, too.
Although it was a bit rough!
フッ ごめん
Sorry.
I'm convinced that the place you remember must still exist somewhere.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 思い出[おもいで]:memories/recollections/reminiscence, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
きっと まだどこかにあるよ
思い出の場所
Yeah...
会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association
じゃあ また会えるといいね
Okay, I hope we can meet again.
迷う[まよう]:to lose one's way|to waver|to give into temptation|
（タケル）もう迷うなよ！
Don't get lost anymore!
Okay!
さようなら:good-bye
うん さようなら
Goodbye!
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
（ヤサコ）ただいま
I'm home...
You came back, finally.
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 帰り[かえり]:return/coming back, やっぱり:too/also|still, 迷子になる[まいごになる]:to get lost/to become lost/to go astray
（静江）やっとお帰りね
やっぱり迷子になったんでしょ？
So you did indeed get lost.
I don't know.
（ヤサコ）知らない
Someone called you.
電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device)
電話あったわよ
（ヤサコ）誰から？
Who?
Your teacher at the Kanazawa school, Mr. Ishida.
担任[たんにん]:in charge (of something)|class teacher/homeroom teacher, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
（静江）金沢で担任だった石田(いしだ)先生
What did he say?
それで なんだって？
You had a friend called Mayumi, right?
マユミ:Japanese spindle tree (Euonymus sieboldianus), 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
マユミちゃんって友達いたでしょ
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, メガネ:spectacles/glasses, 遊び[あそび]:playing|play (margin between on and off, gap before pressing button or lever has an effect)
ほら いつも一緒に
メガネ遊びしてた
A girl you always used to play glasses with...
She's going to move to Hokkaido.
北海道[ほっかいどう]:Hokkaido (island, prefectural-level administrative unit), 引っ越す[ひっこす, ひきこす]:to move (house)/to change residence
あの子ね
もうすぐ北海道に引っ越すんだって
仲[なか]:relation/relationship, 仲[すあい, すわい]:broker/brokerage/brokerage fee, 良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|, わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（静江）優子と仲良かったからって
わざわざ連絡くだすったのよ
He phoned because you and she were good friends.
This is Mayumi's phone number.
マユミ:Japanese spindle tree (Euonymus sieboldianus), 連絡先[れんらくさき]:contact address
これ マユミちゃんの連絡先だって
He sure was a mysterious boy...
不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange, 男の子[おとこのこ, おとこのコ]:boy/male child/baby boy, 男の子[おのこ]:man/boy
（ヤサコ）不思議な男の子だったな
But thanks to him, I remembered something.
おかげ:grace (of God)/benevolence (of Buddha)|assistance, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect
でも おかげで
ちょっとだけ思い出せたわ
That Illegal...
イリーガル:illegal
あのイリーガル…
And then 4-4-2-3...
それに ４４２３…
I wonder if they're real or not...
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 現実[げんじつ]:reality/actuality/hard fact, かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
ホントに現実だったのかしら？
May this is just a record I made of some dream I had?
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage, 描く[えがく, かく]:to draw|to depict|to picture in one's mind|
（ヤサコ）
これも夢の記憶を描いたのかな？
Or...
それとも…
Yeah...
Yeah.
It wasn't in that Space.
空間[くうかん]:space/room/airspace, 空間[あきま]:vacancy/room for rent or lease
あの空間にはなかった
But I accidentally got to know something interesting.
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy), 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant, 知り合う[しりあう]:to get to know (someone)/to make acquaintance
それより 偶然
面白い子と知り合ったんだ
Yeah.
イマーゴ:imago, 子供[こども]:child/children
うん イマーゴの子供だと思う
I think she's an Imago kid.
Yeah...
そう
Just like that Kanna girl.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
あのカンナって子と同じに…
Preview
Next time
on Dennou Coil:
Isako's hospital room.
Isako's Hospital Room
See you next time.
次回[じかい]:next time (occasion), 電脳[でんのう]:computer|cyberbrain/digital brain, コイル:coil
（ヤサコ）
次回 「電脳コイル」
病室[びょうしつ]:sickroom/hospital room
〝イサコの病室 〞
楽しみ[たのしみ]:enjoyment/pleasure|anticipation
お楽しみに